Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5728
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
1969-1985
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association (RLEA)
5728
58 cubic feet
58 linear ft.
Records (documents), newspaper clippings.
This collection consists of the general and office files of the Railway Labor Executives' Association for the years 1973-1985.
3123465
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
JH, November 18, 2014
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 12, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The RLEA was founded in 1926 in response to the passage of the Railway Labor Act. Prior to 1926, there had been an informal association between the railroad labor organizations so that the various chief executives of the different unions could work together to form a unified course of action that would benefit all of their members. This group became more formalized immediately after the end of WW1. The U.S. railroads had been nationalized as part of the war effort, and the railroad labor organizations wanted them to remain under federal management, both because of increased productivity and because of better labor relations with the industry. The effort was ultimately unsuccessful, and the railroads returned to private industry; however, the railroad labor organizations had realized the need to have a united front to counter the carriers and industry groups and lobbyists.
On May 18, 1926, the chief executives of the railroad labor organization met in Washington D.C., formalized their association with By-Laws, and elected officers to serve the newly created RLEA. The original purpose, codified in the original preamble, was co-operative action to obtain and develop consistent interpretations and utilization of the Railway Labor Act. The RLEA was comprised of the chief executives of the 21 railroad labor unions, including the president of the Railway Employees' Department of the AFL, and each member got one vote, regardless of the size of their union. The organization was voluntary, so no member organization was bound by its decisions. Over the course of its existence, various member organizations withdrew and then re-affiliated with the RLEA.
From 1926 to 1938, the RLEA did not maintain an office, but the amount of work and its importance led the RLEA to open an office in Washington DC and employ a full-time Executive Secretary- Treasurer to run it. The RLEA did not engage in collective bargaining itself, but rather lobbied on behalf of its member organizations, securing such achievements as the Railroad Retirement Act and limiting unemployment for its members during the Great Depression. The RLEA's various areas of interest, such as retirement, safety, legal matters, were broken down into committees, each of which reported back to the executive board on the steps being taken in those areas.
Post WW2, the RLEA played a central role in the Marshall Plan, working with non-Communist labor organizations in Western Europe to establish labor policy and also assist in the work of rebuilding the European railroads. The RLEA was also a major factor in international labor union federations, and its decision to affiliate with the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITWF) and to encourage the ITWF not to join with the Soviet affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions was seen as a major victory for the west.
The RLEA, like its member organizations, did not allow African-American members. As such, it was only representing the interests of white railroad employees; black railroad employees were forced, for the most part, to work without recognized union protection. The exception to this was the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (BSCP), who in 1948 began a series of successful legal challenges to the jurisdictions over various classes of work. As BSCP's successes in the courts mounted up, and the RLEA's member unions and the RLEA itself were being sued for discriminatory practices, the RLEA finally capitulated in 1950, and accepted the BSCP as a member organization.
In 1950, the RLEA joined with the AFL, CIO, and International Association of Machinists to form the United Labor Policy Committee. This committee oversaw the labor representatives of the Wage Stabilization Board.
In the latter half of the 20th century, the importance of the RLEA declined alongside the decline in the railroad industry itself. As its member unions either merged into single entities or disaffiliated from the RLEA its influence waned, as did the number of its members. The RLEA attempted to counter this decline with the purchase of a railroad at least three different times in the 1970s and 1980s, though they were ultimately unsuccessful in this venture. Ongoing internal battles between the remaining chief executives of the railroad unions further weakened the RLEA until in 1997 it disbanded, handing over its responsibilities to the newly formed AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1969-1985
Bulk dates: 1973-1984
This collection consist of the office and files for the years 1973 through 1984. The office files from 1983 are not included, but desk and reader files for 1983 may be found in Series XV. This collection also contains the general office files of the Congress of Railway Unions for 1969 through 1975.
The Congress of Railway Unions [CRU] was formed during December 1969 after five unions withdrew from the Railway Labor Executives' Association over a dispute involving proposed compulsory retirement and pension benefit legislation (see Collection 5552). The six organizations who founded this group were the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes [BMoW], the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline, and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employes [BRAC], the United Transportation Union [UTU], Transit Workers' Union [TWU], Seafarers' International Union of North America [SIU], and the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union [HERE]. The RLEA and the Congress of Railway Unions worked together after their split to protect their members during the numerous mergers and bankruptcies that were affecting the industry at this time. The CRU acted as a policymaking body on legislation and other matters of interest to railroad workers in an identical capacity to the RLEA. In 1974, the two groups reached an accord and decided to re-affiliate. The unification occurred on April 1, 1975. BRAC was not party to the reunification, as it had disaffiliated from CRU in 1974.
The RLEA arranged their records chronologically by year in designated record groups. CRU followed the same file organization, and their records were integrated into RLEA's files when they reunited. These record groups are used for each calendar year. Each record group consists of numerous files, the majority of which are maintained from year to year. Only when the executive council removed a particular issue from their monthly meeting agendas, records related to that issue were removed from the record group. The RLEA created "File Guides" for each year of record keeping; they also maintained CRU's File Guide to differentiate where the file structure differed. Those documents may be found in the collection for select years to help researchers locate specific papers and may be used to track what issues were continued and which were closed.
The record groups used by the RLEA are as follows:
1. Government
2. Judicial
3. Legislation
4. RLEA
5. Railroads
6. Other Organizations
7. International Affairs
8. Commuter Problems
CRU followed the same file structure, with the difference being that Record Group 4 is titled, "Congress of Railway Unions." Additionally, rather than having a Record Group called "Commuter Problems," they used the title "Urban Mass Transportation Administration." These files were integrated into the existing RLEA file structure's corresponding Record Groups with the CRU titles. CRU files in the other record groups have been marked as such.
Additionally, this collection includes RLEA Desk and Reader Files, which contain carbon copies and select attachments of the outgoing correspondence of RLEA executives and select committees.
The Government Records Group includes files on the following: Railroad Retirement Board; Medicare; President's Committee on Physically Handicapped; Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC); Civil Rights Act; Federal Housing Administration; State Department; Pan American Railway Conference; Department of Transportation; Interstate Commerce Commission; National Transportation Safety Board; National Mediation Board; National Railroad Adjustment Board; Bureau of Labor Statistics; the creation of Amtrak; the creation and sale of ConRail; Federal Railroad Administration; Labor Department; the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA); and files for each of the three branches of government.
The Judicial Records Group includes files on the following: the bankruptcy proceedings of the Penn Central, Boston and Maine, Lehigh Valley, Erie-Lackawanna, Reading Railroad, and Central of New Jersey; the bankruptcy proceedings of the Chicago, Milwaukee, Saint Paul and Pacific Railroad Company (The Milwaukee Road); the bankruptcy proceedings of the Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railroad Company (The Rock Island); filings by the RLEA in various bankruptcy courts and courts of appeal to protect employees of these bankrupt railroad companies; filings by the RLEA in regards to the constitutionality of railroad reorganization legislation; a lawsuit against Conrail to prevent random drug and alcohol testing of employees. The case against Conrail and matters in re employee protections in bankruptcy proceeding were both appealed all the way to the U.S. Supreme Court. See also RLEA files labelled "Lawyer's Bills," which contain itemized lists of legal matters the RLEA was involved in according to the bills of their general counsel.
The Legislation Records Group includes files on the following: applications for capital improvement grants by urban municipalities under the Urban Mass Transit Act of 1964; amendments to the Railroad Retirement Act; the Amtrak Improvement Act of 1973; and legislation in regards to the Northeast Rail Crisis, which was sparked by the bankruptcies of major rail carriers and lead to the creation of Amtrak and Conrail. For the years after 1973, legislative matters are housed in other Record Groups. The Government Records Group includes files on the sale of Conrail by the Reagan administration and the legislation surrounding its purchase (the NERSA Act). Files concerning the legislation that deregulated the railroad industry: the Regional Rail Reorganization Act of 1973 (3Rs Act), the Railroad Revitalization and Regulatory Reform Act of 1976 (4Rs Act), and the Staggers Rail Act of 1980, are located both in the Government Records Group and in the RLEA Record Group's Legislative Committee files.
The RLEA Records Group includes files on the following: constitutions and by-laws; correspondence files for each of their member organizations; minutes from monthly meetings, agendas for the monthly meetings; planning documents for the monthly February meeting in Miami, Florida; information on general office matters; insurance plans; Wage and Rules Movements; reports from RLEA committees; bills; and plans and proposals for their attempt to purchase Conrail from the U.S. government.
The CRU Records Group, which is filed with the 1974 RLEA Record Group, contains their records from 1969-1974. They were interfiled with the RLEA records when the two organizations reunited. The CRU Records Group follows the same file schema as RLEA. For more information on these records, please see Series III below.
The Railroads Records Group includes files on the following: the bankruptcy proceedings of Northeast carriers [n.b.: the bulk of the records concerning the Penn Central bankruptcy are found in collections 5484 and 5552]; correspondence files with industry groups that represent carriers; filing by RLEA and CRU with various courts to compel bankrupt carriers to honor employee protection agreements; and reports on the financial health of carriers' hospital associations.
The Other Organization Records Group includes files on the following: the AFL-CIO and its various departments; the National Association of Railroad Passengers (NARP); Labor newspaper; National Safety Council; and various charitable organizations supported by the RLEA.
The International Affairs Records Group shows the sharpest divide between the RLEA and CRU. After the organizations split, the membership in international trade groups was maintained by CRU but not by RLEA. The RLEA records reflect this, and only contain select newsletters and correspondence with the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITF) and its various departments and reports on foreign railroaders participating in exchange programs. CRU, on the other hand, maintained their affiliation with ITF, and their International Affairs records group includes files on their role in the ITF, as well as files on foreign visitors and their involvement in the Pan-American Railway Congress. See Series III for more detail.
The Commuter Problems Records Group includes files on applications for federal grants by urban transit authorities including New York City and the New York metropolitan area, Chicago, the Bay Area, Washington DC, New Haven, and Philadelphia. Also found in this Record Group are filings of Section 13(c) Agreements, employee protective agreements between transit authorities and railway labor unions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5552: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5300: Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 6087: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
Arrangement
Series I: Office Files, 1973
Series II: Desk Files, 1973
Series III: Office Files, 1974
Series IV: Office Files, 1975
Series V: Office Files, 1976
Series VI: Office Files, 1977
Series VII: Office Files, 1978
Series VIII: Office Files, 1979
Series IX: Desk Files, 1975
Series X: Office Files, 1980
Series XI: Office Files, 1981
Series XII: Desk Files, 1981
Series XIV: Office Files, 1984
Series XIII: Office Files, 1982
Series XV: Desk and Reader Files, 1975-1985
Medicare; Strikes and lockouts -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Bankruptcy -- United States; Railroad law -- United States; Local transit -- Law and legislation -- United States; Urban transportation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions; Railroads -- Finance -- United States; ConRail -- Appropriations and expenditures; ConRail -- Finance; Railroads -- Northeastern States; Railroads -- Northeastern States -- Finance; Railroads -- Northeastern States -- Freight; Railroads and state -- United States; Railway Labor Executives' Association; Congress of Railway Unions; Travelers Insurance Companies; AFL-CIO; American Railway Supervisors Association; American Train Dispatchers Association; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters; Hotel & Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union; International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers; International Brotherhood of Blacksmiths, Drop Forgers, and Helpers; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; International Organization of Masters, Mates, and Pilots; National Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (U.S.); Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Railroad Yardmasters of America; Railway Employes' Department, AFL-CIO; Sheet Metal Workers' International Association; Switchmen's Union of North America; Transportation Communications International Union; Seafarers' International Union of North America; United Transportation Union; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; United States. Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act; United States. Department of State; Congreso Panamericano de Ferrocarriles; United States. Department of Transportation; United States. National Transportation Safety Board; United States. Federal Railroad Administration; United States. Bureau of Labor; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. National Mediation Board; United States. National Railroad Adjustment Board; United States. President's Committee on Employment of the Physically Handicapped; Amtrak; Penn Central Transportation Company; Association of American Railroads; National Railway Labor Conference (U.S.); Southeastern Pennsylvania Transportation Authority; San Francisco Bay Area Rapid Transit District (Calif.); Port Authority of New York and New Jersey; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority (MBTA); Chicago Transit Authority; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority; International Transport Workers' Federation; Discrimination in employment -- Law and legislation -- United States.; United States. Interstate Commerce Act; United States. Railroad Retirement Act; United States. Railroad Safety Legislation; United States. Railway Labor Act; United States. Social Security Act; United States. Civil Rights Act of 1964; United States. Urban Mass Transportation Act of 1964; United States. Northeast Rail Service Act of 1981; United States. Staggers Rail Act of 1980; United States. Regional Rail Reorganization Act of 1973; United States. Railroad Revitalization and Regulatory Reform Act of 1976; ConRail
3123465
- Series I: Office Files, 1973
  - Government: Constitution, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    No records contained in folder when collection accessioned.
  - Government: Executive Branch, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes Nixon's 1974 State of the Union Address and press releases from the White House, including one in re Nixon's signing of the Amtrak Improvement Act of 1973.
  - Government: House and Senate, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence
  - Government: Congressional Campaign Contribution Requests, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Government: Appointment of Federal Judgeships, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Government: Agencies (General), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Government: State Department (General), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Government: State Department (A.I.D.), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Government: United States National Commission in the Pan American Railway Congress Association, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Government: Treasury Department (General), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Government: Payroll Savings Division, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Government: Internal Revenue Service, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Government: Defense Department (General), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Government: Office of Emergency Planning, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Government: Labor Management Manpower Policy Committee, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Bulletins
  - Government: Regional Manpower Policy Committee, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Government: National Defense Executive Reserves, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Government: Massachusetts Civil Defense Agency - Transportation Task Group, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Government: Department of Transportation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Bulletins and correspondence
  - Government: DOT Staff Appointments, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Government: Transportation Association of America, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Correspondence and reports in re awarding of the E.H. Harriman Awards for carriers with the best safety record.
  - Government: Department of Transportation Studies, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Government: National Transportation Safety Board [folder 1 of 2], 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23a)
    Bulletins, safety studies, and accident reports
  - Government: National Transportation Safety Board [folder 2 of 2], 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23b)
  - Government: Federal Railroad Administration, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes invitation to tour the high-speed testing grounds in Pueblo, Colorado and a map of the facilities. Also includes summary of meeting with FRA administrators in re the problems arising from the Penn Central bankruptcy.
  - Government: Staff Appointments (Federal Railroad Administration, F.R.A.), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Government: Office of High Speed Ground Transportation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Government: Studies and Reports, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Accident reports.
  - Government: Office of Railroad Safety, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Includes accident reports.
  - Government: Railroad Safety Task Force, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Report from the "Task Force on Terminals."
  - Government: Safety - Rules, Regulations, Petitions (Federal Railroad Administration - Department of Transportation), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes petition from Penn Central to receive a temporary waiver from complying with FRA track safety standards because of a lack of funds. Also includes correspondence from RLEA member organizations to the FRA in re occupational safety standards.
  - Government: Highway Grade Crossing Matters, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Accident reports and conference proceedings.
  - Government: Power Brakes, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Government: Study Group on Advanced Coupling Concepts, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Government: Locomotive Inspection, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Government: Signal Rules, Standards, and Instructions (R. S. and I. Cases), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Public notices.
  - Government: Approval of Changes in Signal Installations (BS-AP Cases), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Government: Hours of Service, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Government: Track Maintenance and Inspection Standards, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Government: Accident Reports and Governing Regulations, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Includes data sets on accidents.
  - Government: Labor Department (General), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Government: Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Includes drafts of Occupational Outlook Handbook with corrections from the chief executives of RLEA's member organizations and a report on major collective bargaining agreements from the BLS.
  - Government: Bureau of Labor Statistics - Wage Chronology 40 - Non-Operating Employees, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Government: Bureau of Labor Standards, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Government: Bureau of Labor - Management Reports, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Government: Interstate Commerce Commission, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Government: Interstate Commerce Commission Membership and Staff Appointments, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Appointment of Commissioner Kenneth Tuggle to oversee restructuring of Northeastern rails.
  - Government: Interstate Commerce Commission Rules of Practice and Administrative Procedure, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Revised abandonment rules.
  - Government: Interstate Commerce Commission Statistics, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 48)